<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://derek.stride.host/books/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://derek.stride.host/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-22T20:53:20+00:00</updated><id>https://derek.stride.host/books/rss.xml</id><title type="html">derekstride | Books</title><author><name>derekstride</name></author><entry><title type="html">Clear Thinking</title><link href="https://derek.stride.host/books/clear-thinking" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clear Thinking" /><published>2024-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://derek.stride.host/books/clear-thinking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://derek.stride.host/books/clear-thinking"><![CDATA[<p>Clear Thinking is about what happens in the space between stimulus and response. Most of the time we don’t think at
all—we react. Our defaults take over. Parrish argues that mastering these defaults is the key to better outcomes.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>People who master their defaults get the best real-world results. It’s not that they don’t have a temper or an ego,
they just know how to control both rather than be controlled by them. With the ability to think clearly in ordinary
moments today, they consistently put themselves in a good position for tomorrow.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The book is organized around identifying the enemies of clear thinking, then building strength and managing weakness to
overcome them.</p>

<h2 id="the-four-defaults">The Four Defaults</h2>

<p>Parrish identifies four biological defaults that hijack our thinking:</p>

<blockquote>
  <ol>
    <li>The emotion default: we tend to respond to feelings rather than reasons and facts.</li>
    <li>The ego default: we tend to react to anything that threatens our sense of self-worth or our position in a group
hierarchy.</li>
    <li>The social default: we tend to conform to the norms of our larger social group.</li>
    <li>The inertia default: we’re habit forming and comfort seeking. We tend to resist change, and to prefer ideas,
processes, and environments that are familiar.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>These aren’t character flaws—they’re features of human biology. The goal isn’t to eliminate them but to recognize when
they’re taking over.</p>

<h2 id="the-stimulus-response-gap">The Stimulus-Response Gap</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the space between stimulus and response, one of two things can happen. You can consciously pause and apply reason
to the situation. Or you can cede control and execute a default behavior. … So our first step in improving our
outcomes is to train ourselves to identify the moments when judgment is called for in the first place, and pause to
create space to think clearly.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This connects directly to habit awareness in <a href="/books/atomic-habits">Atomic Habits</a>—the first step before you can change
a habit is noticing the cue that triggers it.</p>

<h2 id="environment-over-willpower">Environment Over Willpower</h2>

<p>One of the most practical insights: don’t fight your defaults with willpower. Change your environment instead.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What may look like discipline often involves a carefully created environment to encourage certain behaviors. The way
to improve your defaults isn’t by willpower but by creating an intentional environment where your desired behavior
becomes the default behavior.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This reinforces the core message from <a href="/books/atomic-habits">Atomic Habits</a>: design your environment to make the right
behavior easy and the wrong behavior hard.</p>

<h2 id="halt">HALT</h2>

<p>A simple check before making decisions:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>HALT—an acronym that stands for Hungry, Angry, Lonely, and Tired. Ask yourself whether any of these conditions apply.
If so, deal with the real problem first.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Originally from Alcoholics Anonymous, but broadly applicable. Don’t make important decisions when your defaults are
primed to take over.</p>

<h2 id="decision-making-principles">Decision-Making Principles</h2>

<p>Parrish offers several practical principles for better decisions:</p>

<p><strong>The 3+ Principle:</strong></p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Force yourself to explore at least three possible solutions to a problem. If you find yourself considering only two
options, force yourself to find at least one more.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>The Bad Outcome Principle:</strong></p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Don’t just imagine the ideal future outcome. Imagine the things that could go wrong and how you’ll overcome them if
they do.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>The Definition Principle:</strong></p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Take responsibility for defining the problem. Don’t let someone define it for you. Do the work to understand it. Don’t
use jargon to describe or explain it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>On Low-Stakes Decisions:</strong></p>
<blockquote>
  <p>When the stakes are low, inaction hurts you more than speed. Sometimes it’s better just to make a quick choice and not
spend time deliberating.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="handling-mistakes">Handling Mistakes</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>The four steps to handling mistakes more effectively are as follows:</p>

  <ol>
    <li>accept responsibility</li>
    <li>learn from the mistake</li>
    <li>commit to doing better</li>
    <li>repair the damage as best you can</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="self-knowledge">Self-Knowledge</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you play games where other people have the aptitude and you don’t, you’re going to lose. You have to figure out
where you have an edge and stick to it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Know your strengths, play where you have an advantage.</p>

<h2 id="learning-from-experts">Learning From Experts</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>People at the far right of the bell curve (the positive outliers) can teach you tips, tricks, and insights that might
otherwise take a lifetime to learn. They’ve done the heavy lifting. They’ve already paid for the lessons, so you don’t
have to.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Seek out exemplars. Learn from people who’ve already solved the problems you’re facing.</p>]]></content><author><name>Shane Parrish</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Master your defaults. The gap between stimulus and response is where clear thinking happens—or doesn't.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Atomic Habits</title><link href="https://derek.stride.host/books/atomic-habits" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atomic Habits" /><published>2022-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://derek.stride.host/books/atomic-habits</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://derek.stride.host/books/atomic-habits"><![CDATA[<p>The biggest takeaway: environment beats willpower. Instead of relying on discipline to build good habits or break bad ones, design your surroundings to make the right behavior easy and the wrong behavior hard. Want to read more? Put a book on your pillow. Want to eat healthier? Keep fruit on the counter and hide the snacks. The goal is to reduce friction for what you want to do and increase friction for what you don’t.</p>

<h2 id="outcomes-are-lagging-indicators">Outcomes Are Lagging Indicators</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Your outcomes are a lagging measure of your habits. Your net worth is a lagging measure of your financial habits. Your weight is a lagging measure of your eating habits. Your knowledge is a lagging measure of your learning habits. Your clutter is a lagging measure of your cleaning habits. You get what you repeat.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This complements <a href="/books/deep-work">Deep Work</a>’s advice to <strong>act on the lead measures</strong>. You can’t directly control outcomes, but you can control the habits that produce them.</p>

<h2 id="the-laws-of-behavior-change">The Laws of Behavior Change</h2>

<p>Clear provides a practical framework for building good habits (or breaking bad ones):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The 1st Law of Behavior Change is to make it obvious. Strategies like implementation intentions and habit stacking are among the most practical ways to create obvious cues for your habits and design a clear plan for when and where to take action.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sometimes a habit will be hard to remember and you’ll need to make it obvious. Other times you won’t feel like starting and you’ll need to make it attractive. In many cases, you may find that a habit will be too difficult and you’ll need to make it easy. And sometimes, you won’t feel like sticking with it and you’ll need to make it satisfying.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="environment-over-willpower">Environment Over Willpower</h2>

<p>Shane Parrish’s <em>Clear Thinking</em> reinforces this idea:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What may look like discipline often involves a carefully created environment to encourage certain behaviors. <strong>The way to improve your defaults isn’t by willpower but by creating an intentional environment where your desired behavior becomes the default behavior.</strong></p>

  <p>— <em>Clear Thinking</em> by Shane Parrish</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Parrish also describes why habits are so powerful (and hard to change):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>The inertia default</strong>: we’re habit forming and comfort seeking. We tend to resist change, and to prefer ideas, processes, and environments that are familiar.</p>

  <p>— <em>Clear Thinking</em> by Shane Parrish</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="the-stimulus-response-gap">The Stimulus-Response Gap</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the space between stimulus and response, one of two things can happen. You can consciously pause and apply reason to the situation. Or you can cede control and execute a default behavior. … So our first step in improving our outcomes is to train ourselves to identify the moments when judgment is called for in the first place, and pause to create space to think clearly.</p>

  <p>— <em>Clear Thinking</em> by Shane Parrish</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This speaks to habit awareness—the first step before you can change a habit is noticing the cue that triggers it.</p>

<h2 id="repeat-what-works">Repeat What Works</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you’re doing something that doesn’t get you the results you want, try something new. If you’re doing something that seems to work, keep doing it. <strong>Consistently repeat successful actions.</strong></p>

  <p>— <em>Letting the World Do the Work for You</em>, Farnam Street</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is the essence of Atomic Habits in one line: find what works, then repeat it relentlessly.</p>]]></content><author><name>James Clear</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Design your environment to promote the habits you want. Add cues for habits you're building, remove triggers for habits you're breaking.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Work</title><link href="https://derek.stride.host/books/deep-work" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Work" /><published>2021-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://derek.stride.host/books/deep-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://derek.stride.host/books/deep-work"><![CDATA[<p>Deep work is Valuable, Rare, &amp; Meaningful. This is the premise of the first section of <em>Deep Work</em> by Cal Newport.  The
second section of the book is devoted to strategies to improving your abilities to perform deep work more frequently and
for longer durations.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Deep Work: Professional activities performed in a state of distraction-free concentration that push your cognitive
capabilities to their limit. These efforts create new value, improve your skill, and are hard to replicate.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I subscribe to the belief that deep work is valuable, rare, &amp; meaningful. I did not need much convincing of this, as I
have spent a considerable amount of effort in my life optimizing my ability to perform deep work (although, I did not
know it by that name). If you do not agree with the premise of the book, I suggest that you still give the first part of
a read as Newport does a much better of explaining it than I can in these notes.</p>

<p>The counterpart to deep work is shallow work. Shallow work is not presented in a good light because it is a source of
distraction, which pulls away from deeper work. An often-cited strategy to efficiently completing shallow work is to
<em>batch</em> it into chunks, so it does not permeate through your schedule.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Shallow Work: Noncognitively demanding, logistical-style tasks, often performed while distracted. These efforts tend
to not create much new value in the world and are easy to replicate.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="going-deeper">Going Deeper</h2>

<p>The second section of the book provides rules aimed to improve our deep work frequency and duration. While I do not find
the names of the rules particularly helpful, I hope to summarize a few ideas that I took from the second section of the
book.</p>

<h3 id="strategies-to-improving-depth">Strategies to Improving Depth</h3>

<h4 id="1---decide-on-your-depth-philosophy-of-deep-work-scheduling">1 - Decide on your Depth Philosophy of Deep Work Scheduling</h4>

<p>The Monastic approach to deep work scheduling is the most aggressive and unapproachable. It is strict adherence to a
schedule that makes you unreachable from the day-to-day of people outside your circles. To get a better sense of the
approach let’s first look at the next philosophy and an example given by Newport.</p>

<p>The Bimodal approach to deep work scheduling has the individual work in 2 modes of operation: monastic and open. The
example given by Newport is a professor who loads all their teaching responsibilities into the fall semester then
devotes the rest of the academic year to a monastic-style research schedule with few other responsibilities.</p>

<p>The rhythmic approach to deep work scheduling is the most appealing to me as it involves scheduling daily stretches of
deep work while allowing the flexibility of life to intermingle. The rhythmic approach assumes that during the deep work
hours of your day you are in strict adherence to a deep work ritual.</p>

<p>The journalistic approach to deep work scheduling is an ad hoc approach that involves taking advantage of sporadic
breaks to make progress on deep work. It is advertised as an approach only for veterans of deep work.</p>

<h4 id="2---ritualize">2 - Ritualize</h4>

<blockquote>
  <p>Managing distractions through habits, rituals, and your environment is key to with-standing the daily erosion of your
<strong>finite</strong> willpower.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Schedule every minute of your day. Schedule what you will do and when. Do not mistake this as making your days rigid;
flexibility and adaptation are encouraged and expected! The point is to structure your time so that distractions cannot
easily take hold of your attention. It is just as important to structure your environment. I began an experiment to
limit the effect that my phone plays in distracting me. My colleague <a href="https://maximevaillancourt.com/">Maxime
Vaillancourt</a> wrote an excellent post on how to turn your phone into a tool titled
<a href="https://maximevaillancourt.com/blog/turning-my-smartphone-into-a-boring-tool">Turning my smartphone into a boring
tool</a>. I want to take it further by
experimenting with leaving it at my door and only carry it when I am leaving the house.</p>

<h4 id="3---the-grand-gesture">3 - The Grand Gesture</h4>

<p>Spending a lot of money on something will trick your brain into believing it is important. Newport gives the extreme
example of an author who buys a round-trip flight to Japan from the USA. The author did this to help focus on coming up
with an outline for their upcoming book.</p>

<p>This is helpful to provide you with a new way of prioritizing deep work.</p>

<h4 id="4---dont-work-alone">4 - Don’t Work Alone</h4>

<p>Deep work does not have to be done alone. Working with colleagues is still a form of deep work. From my experience Pair
Programming is an excellent example.</p>

<h4 id="5---execute-like-a-business">5 - Execute Like a Business</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Focus on the wildly important tasks</li>
</ul>

<p>Do not prioritize things of low value. Measure the value of a task.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Act on the lead measures</li>
</ul>

<p>A lead measure is a metric you can measure ahead of time, e.g. the number of deep hours worked. A lag measure is a
metric that cannot be measured until after a goal is met, e.g. number of blog posts written.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Keep a compelling scorecard</li>
</ul>

<p>In the case of deep work, keep a visible scoreboard of the number of deep hours worked per week.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Create a cadence of accountability</li>
</ul>

<p>Review your scoreboard regularly. Ideally, involve a third party to help keep you accountable.</p>

<h4 id="6---be-lazy">6 - Be Lazy</h4>

<p>In line with ritualizing your day, ritualize the end of your workday by logging unfinished tasks so your mind does not
hold onto them. Then end with an audible phrase such as Newport’s own: “Shutdown Complete.” He characterizes this as a
shutdown ritual.</p>

<h3 id="reducing-distractions">Reducing Distractions</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>Boredom must not be fought with distraction.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The idea of boredom is often thought of as something to be avoided, but Newport encourages the reader to embrace
boredom.  In an age of connectedness, our attention is at a premium. Our Brains, a product of human biology, are losing
the competition against technology. Technology evolves at an incredible pace that human evolution cannot fight against.
At the peak of technological tools is social media. Social media monetizes our attention and sells it. Its goal is to
increase the attention we give it.</p>

<p>By contrast, depth requires concentration free from distraction, which positions social media as the natural antagonist.</p>

<p>Newport suggests we adopt the Craftsmen approach to tool selection: weighing the benefits of social media outlets
against the consequences. This is opposed to the Any-benefit approach which states that if the media outlet has any
value, then we should consider using it.</p>

<p>To help with the application of the craftsmen approach to tool selection, Newport gives us 3 processes for evaluating
the benefits of social media.</p>

<h4 id="1---law-of-the-vital-few">1 - Law of the Vital few.</h4>

<p>Often known as the 80/20 rule. To estimate value, come up with a few specific goals and see if social media helps you
reach them.</p>

<h4 id="2---quit-social-media">2 - Quit Social Media.</h4>

<p>Quit social media for 30 days without telling anyone unless asked. If at the end of those 30 days, your lack of presence
made a negative effect on your goals, then return.</p>

<h4 id="3---do-not-use-the-internet-to-entertain-yourself">3 - Do not use the internet to entertain yourself.</h4>

<p>Social media is too dangerous to use as entertainment, other alternatives are better. Use it as a tool, not an outlet
for solving boredom.</p>

<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>I intend to put into practice many of these suggestions to help hone my deep work skills. I hope to improve.</p>]]></content><author><name>Cal Newport</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Deep work is Valuable, Rare, &amp; Meaningful. This is the premise of the first section of Deep Work by Cal Newport. The second section of the book is devoted to strategies to improving your abilities to perform deep work more frequently and for longer durations.]]></summary></entry></feed>